This video describes the technique for examining pupils.
First, perform hand hygiene, don PPE if required.
Introduce yourself, explain the examination and gain consent.
Pause briefly to observe the eyes, giving particular attention to the appearance of the pupils.
Comment on any relative difference in size, colour and shape,
as well as any evidence of ptosis or squint.
If there is any difference in pupil size known as
an isochoria, then an efferent problem may be present.
Observe in dimmer, then brighter lighting conditions to see if it accentuates any difference.
Next, ask the patient to fix on a distance target and examine the pupil
responses in a dimly lit room using the brightest light setting of the arc
light loop.
Now test and observe the three light responses.
Start with the direct response by observing the illuminated pupil.
Then examine the consensual response by observing the other pupil that is not being directly illuminated.
Thirdly, look for a relative afferent papillary defect, often shortened to REPD, by using the
swinging light test.
The key to performing this test is to swiftly move the light between the
two eyes before
the pupil has time to escape.
But then wait for 2-3 seconds, for the pupil to stabilise, observing carefully for any overall
change in size.
In younger people you may notice a brief period of fluctuation as the pupil
bounces up and
down before settling.
This is called hippus in as normal.
During the swaying light test if
the pupil paradoxically dilates when light is shown upon it, an RAPD is present.
In this
examination the left pupil dilates when illuminated.
A left RAPD is therefore present.
This strongly
suggests that there is pathology of either the retina or optic nerve on the left side.
The final test is the near response.
Ask the patient to fix in a distance target, then ask
them to look at a detailed near target such as the bird on the
Arclight. This induces
miosis.
You have now completed the pupil examination.
Thank the patient and explain and record your
findings, finishing by repeating hand hygiene.